# 嗨喽 大家好
Hello everyone
# 今天我们用这个n清明菜
Today we’ll use this Qingming herb (Gnaphalium Affine)
# 这个清明菜在我们这里叫燕子花
which is also called saw-wings flower around our place
# 我们做一个清明节美食
to make a traditional refreshment for the Qingming Festival
# 这屋头还是有这个菜噶
We still have this herb around the house?
# 有
Sure
# 反正就是清明的时候吃嘛
Usually we have this around the Qingming Festival
# 如果你们在农村的话可以弄这个来吃一下
You can get some of this herb to try if you live in the countryside
# 这个的话还有一些特殊的功效
The herb also has some special benefits
# 它有清热降火 还有润肺的一些功能
It clears the internal heat and nourishes the lungs
# 可以了吗
Enough?
# 可以了
Enough
# 差不多了
Seems about right
# 够了吗这点
Seems too little to me
# 够不够哦
Do we have enough?
# 够得到
It’s enough
# 差不多了
Seems about right
# 害怕整多了到时候是苦的吃起不好吃
If we put too much herb in there, the rice cake is going to taste bitter
# 嗯
Alright
# 要焯过水这个
We need to blanch the herb first
# 必须焯 不焯它就有股酸味
Yeah it’s necessary, otherwise it is too sour
# 我们这个清明菜焯完水之后就变得非常绿
The herb becomes very green after blanching
# 很要绿这个焯了水之后
It looks so green after blanching
# 然后我们取出一半来把它切碎做那个馅
Then we mince half of these for the filling
# 我今天准备的馅料有这个香肠
I got some sausages for the filling today
# 我们四川的麻辣香肠
Our Sichuan style spicy sausage
# 准备一条给它切成颗粒
We take one sausage and dice it
# 如果你们没有香肠的也可以用腊肉
You can also use the Chinese cured pork if you don’t have the sausage
# 而且加新鲜肉也是可以的
Fresh ground pork can also do it
# 只不过用麻辣香肠的话味道会更好一些
The sausage tastes a little better though
# 然后我们横过来切成小颗粒
Then we turn it around and dice it up
# 我们的这个香肠随便剁一下就可以了
Then chop the pieces for several times
# 好了 现在剩下的我们用这个石臼把它捣碎
Alright, then we mush the sausage in this mortar
# 如果你们家里面有料理机的话可以用料理机来打
You can also use a blender if you have one
# 好了 捣烂了
Alright it’s done
# 然后我们捣碎了之后把它舀出来
Then we scoop it into a bowl
# 现在是这个样子
It looks like this now
# 现在我们来调这个粉
Now let’s make the pastry dough
# 然后加点这个粘米粉
First add some (regular) rice flour
# 再加点糯米粉
Then some glutinous rice flour
# 粘米粉和糯米粉的比例一比一就可以了
The regular/glutinous rice flour ratio is 1:1
# 然后我们再加一点盐
Then add some salt in there
# 你一比一没得嫩糍的哦
Your 1:1 ratio will make it too dry
# 嗯 差不多就行了
Emmm, it should be okay
# 糯米粉多加点的
I would add some more glutinous rice flour
# 我们捣好这个清明菜的汁现在我们把它挤进去
Now we squeeze the Qingming herb juice in there
# 要的就是这个颜色
This is the color we want
# 好了 加（汁）水挤进去了我们把它拌匀
Then we knead it well
# 我们这个面和好了之后再把这个渣加进去
After we have the dough, we’ll add the herb in there
# 把这个原渣加进去给它一起挼
Knead all the herb into the dough
# 四伯爷你帮我揉到
Uncle, can you help me knead the dough?
# 我去把那个腊肉（香肠）弄来炒起
I’ll go stir fry the cured pork (sausage)
# 我先是在手头把它搓圆
First we rub it into a ball
# 是搓圆了样
Into a ball, done
# 搓圆了你摊在手头
Then put the ball in the middle of your hand
# 然后就捏边边
Nip the sides
# 你要记到捏边边不能捏中间
Be careful to only nip the sides and leave the center alone
# 中间要稍微厚点的都不关事
The center of the pastry can stay a little thicker
# 呐 这样子它就圆了
Like this round
# 放在手头 手弄来窝起
Put the pastry on your fingers and curl your fingers
# 这样子窝起然后舀一勺进去
Scoop some filling onto the center of the pastry
# 这就圆了撒
I’ve made my pastry round
# 然后这里给它稍微捏一哈 跟包包子一样
Then we nip the edge of the pastry like we are making a dumpling
# 捏拢了之后再搓
After the pastry edges meet, we rub it
# 这（馅料）没有放点猪油在里头炒啊
Did you stir fry the filling with some lard?
# 那个香肠里头就有猪油撒
We already have lard in the sausage
# 猪油少了 我的估计
I don't think we have enough lard in the filling
# 不少不少 都可以了
It should be okay
# 这样子摆起才好蒸嘛 蒸起才像猪儿粑嘛
Gotta place them like this for steaming. Now they look like piggies
# 不是等哈要塌下来噶
Won’t it collapse a bit later?
# 哦 不是它蒸融了来它要垮下来
Yeah it will collapse after steaming (if we don’t place them like this)
# 垮下来就成了粑粑 圆啾啾的就不好看
If it collapses too much and become flat, it won’t look as nice.
# 我是想到包完了再来摆哈
I thought we were going to place them after we make all of them
# 好了 现在我们弄好了放到（蒸锅）上汽
Alright! Now they are ready for steaming
# 上锅蒸 上汽了之后蒸二十分钟左右就可以吃了
Steam them for about 20 minutes and they will be ready
# 我先拿去蒸起
I’ll go put them on the steamer now
# 好 水已经开了
Alright, the water is already boiling
# 把它盖起
Cover it up
# 哦哟
Whoa!
# 好大一个个的
They are huge
# 这个吃了来才吃那个大的
I’ll have this one first before the biggest one
# 你吃几个哦 吃一个就够了
How many do you want? One is enough
# 我给你拿起来
Let me get this for you
# 这就这样子（夹）撒
I can pick it up myself
# 伯娘吃这个 我帮你拿
Auntie have one too. Let me get one for you
# 好好好 谢谢
Alright, thanks
# 好香啊这个蒸出来
After steaming, it smells fantastic
# 好不好吃哦晓得
I wonder how it tastes
# 这个皮子逮到 我把它弄下来
The leaf is stuck on the cake. Let me peel it off
# 把它剁下来
Cut it off
# 跟它弄的糍粑样
It is almost like a "Ciba" (rice pounded cake)
# 安逸
Nice!
# 要巴起
Look at him eating so happily
# 伯娘你笑啥子
Auntie, what are you laughing at?
# 笑啥子哦笑
Yeah, what are you laughing at?
# 你莽起笑 等我个人吃
Go ahead laughing. I’ll enjoy myself.
# 真的吗假的哦 各自吃完
Seriously? Have them all like you can
# 我伯娘笑我伯爷说这个吃了会粘牙齿 其实没什么
My auntie is mocking at my uncle that the sticky cake will stick on his teeth. It should not be that bad I guess
# 很香真的很香
It’s really really good
# 是香啊
Yeah it is
# 安逸
Nice!
# 好吃 很糍的噶
It is good. It’s very juicy
# 嗯
Yeah
# 如果不想吃得太黏嘴的话就可以多加一点这个米粉
If you don’t like it to be too sticky, you can add more regular rice flour
# 少加一点糯米粉
And hold the glutinous rice flour a little
# 好 本期视频就到这里
Alright, that’s all for this episode
# 大家可以尝试做一下
You guys can try this recipe at home